A Guide to the Papers of John McLaren McBryde, 1900-1907
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Papers of John McLaren McBryde, 1900-1907.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 2/5
7 cu. ft.; 9 boxes
McBryde, John McLaren, 1870-1956
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Known as the "father of VPI," McBryde was the first president to have a relatively free hand in developing the academic program, selecting associates, formulating policies, and planning the physical plant of the College. Major accomplishments of his administration included: establishing position of Dean in 1903-04 to aid in administration duties; reorganizing the curriculum and creating seven new 4- year courses leading to Bachelor of Science degrees; introducing a program of graduate study in 1891 and establishing a Graduate Department, with its own Dean, in 1907; starting the summer school program in 1904. Also during his tenure, McBryde improved and expanded the physical plant, with six buildings being renovated and sixty-seven new buildings constructed. The faculty increased from nine in 1891 to forty-eight in 1907 and enrollment rose from one hundred and thirty-five in 1891 to a peak of seven hundred and twenty-eight in 1904/05. McBryde was also the first president to encourage student activities, as witnessed by the beginning of an athletic program and resumption of publication of the Gray Jacket, as well as the adoption of school colors.
Hazing controversies plagued McBryde's administration, but his handling of the early cases tended to enhance his prestige as well as strengthen the College's image.
Because of declining health, McBryde was granted a six months leave of absence for rest and recuperation from January to June, 1906. During this interval, the Board appointed Ellison Smyth and Theodore Campbell to serve jointly as president of the Campus and designated the Rector, J. Thompson Brown, as official head of the College. McBryde returned to his duties as president, but since his health did not improve, he resigned effective 1 July 1907.
Scope and Content
This collection is primarily correspondence (1900-07), both incoming and outgoing, dealing with pertinent subjects of McBryde's administration, including: Christian case and other hazing problems; Junior class uprising (1904); Jamestown Exposition (1907); fire of 1905; McBryde's refusal of University of Virginia presidency. There is also much routine correspondence including requests for catalogs, letters from concerned parents, and business letters. Included with the 1903 correspondence are letters concerning a typhoid epidemic.
Thirteen volumes of letter books (1900-06) contain copies of outgoing correspondence from McBryde and other members of his administration: C.D. Taliaferro (Secretary to President, Registrar, Acting Treasurer, Superintendent of Book Department); Charles I. Wade (Treasurer, Registrar); Ellison Smyth (Dean). Volume I (14 February 1900 - 5 March 1900) includes some letters signed by McBryde as Director of Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station. Much of 1901-02 correspondence consists of requests and orders for catalogs and books to replenish the library after the Administration Building fire. Volume 7 (19 April 1901 - 23 February 1903) contains two reports from McBryde to Board of Visitors, 1901 and 1902, and a report from McBryde to Joseph W. Southall, Superintendent of Public Instruction. Volume 12 (15 July 1904 - 23 September 1905) contains twenty-eight letters from McBryde to Board of Visitors and others. Volume 13 (25 July 1904-28 September 1905) contains correspondence concerning Sweet Briar Institute and signed by McBryde as Chairman of Executive Committee, Sweet Briar Institute. Most volumes are indexed by recipients of correspondence.
The collection also includes: bibliography of McBryde's writings (1841-1923); annual reports of the president (1891, 1892/93); applications for employment of students (1900/01); bids and contracts (1900-07); correspondence of William Alwood, Professor of Horticulture, Entomology, and Mycology (1901-04); reports to the president and board of visitors (1902-07); shops department records (1902-07); Agriculture Hall material (1905-06); correspondence of Theodore Campbell, first Dean of Academic Department (1905-06); requisitions and orders (1905, 1907/08); fire loss records (1905-07); reports of absentism, tardiness, delinquency, or unsatisfactory work of students (1906/07, 1907/08); Proceedings Had Before the Committee Appointed to Investigate Charges Against the Virginia Polytechnic Institute (23-28 July 1906); and biographical information on McBryde, including newspaper clippings.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in subject files. Boxes 6-9 contain oversized material removed from boxes 1-5. The folder descriptions for boxes 6-9 indicate the folders from which the material was removed.
Index Terms
Persons:
McBryde, John McLaren, 1870-1956
Local Subjects:
Faculty; University Archives
Subjects:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- McBryde, John., President, 1891, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - a: Letter from McBryde appointing a "Committee on publication" consisting of 3 faculty members--Campbell, Williams, and Newman. Due to the lack of enforcement of the by-law requiring that all speeches and paper prepared by students for public delivery or college publication must be read and revised by the president.
  - b: Copy of R.H. Jenell's college account ending March 31, 1891. Includes specific fees.
- Untitled, 1905-1907. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - a: Letter to Mr Brown from Dr. McBryde concerning an architectural argument between Professors Patton and Randolph about Science Hall, March 4,1905.
  - b: Resolution that a salary of $1,000 be assigned to the office of Commandant of Cadets in recognition of the major duties of the position.
  - c: Letter to Dr. Barringer regarding his request to McBryde and concerning Mr Jarnagin and his position at V.P.I., July 2, 1907.
  - d: Letter to Dr. Barringer concerning the payment of the Adams Fund and McBryde's request for executive council meeting immediately, July 31, 1907.
- Christian Case, 1905. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - a: Photocopies of the original documents in the file. The documents originally kept with the McBryde files have been removed and made into a separate collection, Christian Case Papers, Ms1996-026.
- Correspondence (to McBryde), 1902-1907. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - a: Letter referring to the establishment of Pittsburgh Club of V.P.I. from W.B. Moffett class of 1901.
  - b: Negotiation of the Hampton Hodge Property, 1902.
  - c: Correspondence between Dr. True and Dr. McBryde concerning unexplained expenditures of the Agriculture Experiment Station.
  - d: Letters of recommendation from Dr. J.B. Alwood, W.M. Scottand Meade Ferguson, for Dr. Ferguson as director of the Experiment Station.
  - e: Negotiations of the Camper Property.
  - f: Correspondence on the Coulter Affair, trouble with the Junior class, December 1904-January 1905.
  - g: Letters from Dr. Henderson concerning the Typhoid epidemic, 1903.
  - h: Correspondence concerning the dismissal of Dr. Eley by McBryde.
- Originals from 4, Correspondence (to McBryde), 1902-1907. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Correspondence, 1902-1907. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - a: History of financial improvement of V.P.I.
  - b: Letters concerning the selection of Professor A.M. Soule as head of the Agriculture School.
  - c: Statements in regard to Mr. C. Binau's proposal to make uniforms for V.P.I., includes costs and numbers of uniforms.
  - d: Letter concerning the past financial history of V.P.I. from 1891.
  - e: Letters from Dr. Robert C. Price regarding his resignation.
  - f: Deed of lease and conditions for extension of the lease of V.P.I. on "Smithfield."
  - g: January 14, 1905 letter containing statements dealing with the investigation of the dining hall and heating of the barracks.
  - h: Letters from McBryde's brother, Bob.
  - i: Brief financial statement for garden department June 22, 1906 by H.F. Price.
  - j: Notable letterhead form the University of State of Florida, including a picture of the Department of Agriculture.
  - k: Report of the operations of Department of Mechanical Engineering, with recommendations for further development of Mechanical Engineering department submitted by Dr. Randolph.
  - l: 3 Awarded diplomas of a Gold medal at the James Town Exhibition for "Method and Illustrations of Instruction in Dairying and Economic Entomology," "Equipment and Instruction in Technical Education," and "Method of Producing, Transporting and Distributing Pure Milk."
  - m: Newspaper article, "Metallurgy as a Study and as a Profession," Times Dispatch, Richmond Virginia, Sunday paper, September 9, 1906.
  - n: Two Publications by the Virginia Experiment Station, "Soil Inoculation with Artificial Cultures," by Meade Furgeson, and "The Inoculation and Cultivation of Alfalfa," by Andrew m. Soule and Meade Furgeson.
  - o: Quick list of recommendations in the President's report.
- Junior Class Resignation, December 1904-January 1905. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - a: Copy of the actual petition signed by the Junior class resigning from the school.
  - b: Testimony regarding the speech Mr. Tinsley, president of the Junior class, made before the day they resigned from the school.
  - c: Petition of the Senior class to uphold the Junior class decision to resign.
- Faculty-Student Matters, 1900, 1904, n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - a: Resolution and report re: the Brooke investigation.
  - b: Typhoid epidemic, reports and questions.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Camp Manufacturing Company, 1904.
  - d: Letter from headquarters of the Corps of Cadets June 1, 1900, concerning the disorder in the dormitories.
  - e: Gary Case.
  - f: Petition for extended Christmas break.
- Shops Dept. Records, 1904-1909. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Alwood, William, 1901-1904. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - a: Correspondence between J.M. Alwood and Dr. McBryde concerning the Directors changes.
  - b: Letter to McBryde concerning the department of Entomology and Mycology from Alwood, May 1902.
  - c: Submitted statement concerning the finances of the Department of Horticulture, Entomology and Mycology, September 24, 1902.
- Reports on School- Addressed to BOV, 1902-1908. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - a: Report on the Book Department, December 2, 1902.
  - b: Report on the "Book and Uniforms Department," June 12, 1902.
  - c: Annual report of the Department mathematics and Physics by C.E. Vawter, June 1902.
  - d: "Report of the work of the colleges of Agriculture for 1904-05 with recommendations."
  - e: Report of the work and expenditures of the experiment station for 1904-05 with proposed budget and recommendations, 1905-1906.
  - f: Report of the work and expenditures of the college farm for 1904-1905 with proposed budget for 1905-06.
  - g: Statistical forms for the Department of the Interior, Bureau of Education for the school year of 1902-1908.
- Reports on School-Addressed to BOV, 1902-1908. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - a: Financial statement of V.P.I. college account.
  - b: Statements of financial transactions of V.P.I. from June 10, 1899- June 10, 1900.
  - c: Statements of financial transactions of V.P.I. from June 1904-1905.
  - d: List of Faculty and Officers for 1903-04 with salaries listed.
  - e: Financial transactions, June 1901-1902.
  - f: Year end reports written by the department heads, 1906.
- Reports, 1902-1907, n.d. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - a: Case of J.L. Nester March 20, 1907, statements of punishment.
  - b: Request for a Faculty Executive Committee, and Semester general report on School Activity.
  - c: Proposal for organization of the Agricultural Experiment Station, Alwood.
  - d: Professors reports on the Academic year of 1902-1903.
  - e: Letter of recommendation of Dr. Harris Hancock for President of UVa.
  - f: Holdaway's resignation letter from the Dairy Division.
  - g: Semester report 1904 from McBryde to the Board of Visitors.
  - h: Rebuttal and explanations to Dr. Trues criticisms of financial transactions from Dr. McBryde.
  - i: Monthly reports by Mary Lacy librarian from November 1905- June 1906.
  - j: Annual Report, Handwritten 1902-1903.
- Annual Reports, 1901-1909. (Box-folder 1:14)
  - a: Inspection report from Hartford steam boiler.
  - b: Annual report for 1901-1902.
  - c: Annual report for 1904-1905.
  - d: Annual report for 1905-1906.
- Fire Losses/ Barringer Letter, 1905-1909. (Box-folder 1:15)
- Boiler-Ag Hall (plans for), 1905-1906. (Box-folder 1:16)
  - a: Floor plans and a sketch of Ag Building at University of Illinois and University of Ohio.
  - b: Booklet of layout and description (with pictures) of Townshend Hall Ohio State University, 1896.
  - c: Sketched Plans for Ag. Hall, Soil Physics lab.
- Chimney Co., Ag. Hall, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 1:17)
  - a: Specifications for a chimney for V.P.I., September 12, 1906.
  - b: Letter referring to an attorney for V.P.I. had been called upon due to problems that had arisen about the construction of the chimney.
  - c: Card for Weber-Steel Concrete Chimney Co., Chicago.
  - d: Letter addressed to Weber-Steel Concrete Chimney Co. from the Engineer in charge of the project, R. Allan, in reference to the problems with the construction of the chimney.
- Originals from 4: Chimney Co., Ag. Hall, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 1:18)
- Furniture, Heating, Gas-Ag Hall. (Box-folder 1:19)
  - a: Plans and Specifications for fermentation cellars.
  - b: Request for 2000 worth of furniture for Agriculture Hall from the Dean and Director of the Department of Agriculture A. Soule, January 1, 1907.
- Plumbing Specs., Ag. Hall. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - a: Letter with suggestion to change in specifications of Agriculture Hall made by A.M. Soule to professor Randolph.
  - b: Pamphlet on ice machine supplies and pumps: Ice Machine Co., New York.
  - c: Specifications for refrigeration and Ice making plant proposed for V.P.I. by the Carbondale Machine Company, September 20, 1906.
  - d: Proposal for 10 ton refrigerating plant Ice Machine Supply Co.
  - e: Copy of 3 advertisement pamphlets: 1: Carey Machinery and Supply Company, Power Transmission Machinery, 2: Bookcases from g/w Libraries and 3: Portland Sectional Conduit, H.W. Johns-Manville Co.
  - f: Pamphlet advertising the Heim Auto Cordless Steam Dampener.
  - g: Pamphlet advertising the Martin Anti-Friction Rocking Grates.
  - h: Pamphlet advertising the Heim Machine Co., Heim automatic fold collar Shaping machine.
  - i: Refrigerating Machine plans and 20 ton ice plant elevations.
  - j: Information questionnaire for the Triumph Ice Machine Co.
  - k: Tables containing the Statistics for the years 1905-1906 from Alabama to Wyoming, collected by National Association of State Universities: Table no. 1: Students, Institutional Valuation, Max Salaries, Houses in Addition to salary, Teaching Force. Table no. 2: Valuation, Support, Buildings and Income.
  - l: Advertisement for reliance, safety water columns, The Reliance Gauge Column Co.
  - m: Card with diagram on The Squires Steam Trap by Carey Machinery and Supply Co.
- Originals from 20: Plumbing Specs-Ag. Hall. (Box-folder 1:21)
- Government Correspondence, 1898-1902, n.d. (Box-folder 1:22)
  - a: Approved Act, March 3, 1898 fro enforced rules and regulations about the sale of intoxicating liquors to minors or certain students.
  - b: Summary of Alwood's accomplishments as director of Virginia Experiment Station, Names of publications and bulletins.
  - c: Senate Bill no. 308. to amend and re-enact the act to create and maintain a state board of crop and pest commissioners and to define its duties and powers, approved March 5, 1900.
  - d: Certificate from Governor Montague stating that Dr. McBryde appointed delegate to the State Good Roads Convention held in Richmond the 20-21 of March, 1902.
  - e: A request for Dr. McBryde to attend Jefferson Memorial and Interstate Good Roads Convention in Charlottesville, April 1902.
  - f: Report from Mr. Scott, from the Committee on Mines and Mining, submitted the following "Endowment, Etc., of certain schools for benefit of Agriculture and Mechanic arts, Etc."
  - g: House of Representatives report #604, "Bill to apply a portion of proceeds of sale of public lands to the endowment of schools or departments of mining and metallurgy and so forth."
  - h: Letter from Martin Dodge, Director of the United States Department of Agriculture Office of Public Road Inquiries, March 3, 1902.
  - i: Circular from the United States Department of Agriculture Bureau of Chemistry, "A plan for cooperating in the study of available plant food."
  - j: Correspondence from Norfolk and Western Railway, October 1902, regarding the Experiment station.
  - k: Sketch of proposed sewer line, October 29, 1902.
  - l: Petition protesting the inclusion of Fluvanna Co. in the quarantine district from Splenetic Fever, signed by stock owners, cattle dealers and citizens of Fluvanna Co.
  - m: Letter concerning corps trip to the South Carolina, Inter-State and West Indian Exposition in Charleston.
- Miscellaneous -McBryde's interests. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - a: Letter to Amy Murray from Dr. W.H. Drummond supporting her work.
  - b: Advertisements for Miss Amy Murray (Scottish Song and Story.)
  - c: Letter to Dr. McBryde from Amy Murray.
  - d: Report from McBryde as Chair of executive committee about his work at Sweet Briar.
- Agricultural Related Brochures, Office Equipment, 1895-1906. (Box-folder 1:24)
  - a: Catalogues and Advertisements from the following companies:
    - Gunn Sectional Book Cases.
    - Globe-Wernicke Co. Cabinet Supplies, January 1907.
    - Southern Stamp and Stationary Co., April 1907.
    - The Optics of the Field Glass, Bausch and Lomb Optical Co., May 15, 1907.
    - 1904-1905 Everette Waddey Co. Stationary and Office Appliances.
    - Moore's loose leaf record books and cabinets, 1905.
    - J.M. Hanson's Newspaper and Magazine Agency, 1907-1908.
    - J.M. Hanson's Newspaper and Magazine Agency, 1906-1907.
    - Office devices- Aids for the systematic manager, J.P. Bell Company.
    - Tatum loose leaf books, J.P. Bell Company.
    - Mittag and Volger Manufacturer of ribbons and carbon papers.
    - Columbia Typewriter paper, The Columbia Typewriter Mfg. Co.
  - b: Smith's enameled steel signals and alphabets, Charles C. Smith Manufacturers.
  - c: Defiance Company advertisements sent to McBryde:
    - Pocket Poker Chips.
    - Draft and Check Protector, new steel matrix model.
    - Payroll Machine.
    - Wage calculator.
    - Dividend check writer.
    - Initial press.
  - d: J.P. Bell Co. Automatic numbering machine, writing fluid, and ink stand, 1903.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence. (Box-folder 1:25)
  - a: Entomological News, March 1903. Includes plate of Butterfly, By Ellison Smyth Jr.
  - b: "A Chance to Advance Southern Technical Training, January 23, 1903.
  - c: Letter from New Hampshire college of Agriculture and the Mechanic Arts concerning the Government money and experiment stations.
  - d: Check from the Bank of Blacksburg.
  - e: Qualifications for degrees for Electrical Engineering, General Engineering, Agriculture and Mechanical Engineering.
  - f: Statistics of Attendance, November 12, 1903.
  - g: Department of Agriculture and Immigration literature defining the powers and duties of the board of Agriculture.
  - h: Comparison of cost of buildings erected in 1900 by contract and in 1904 by the college itself.
  - i: Schedule of final examinations for the 1903-1904 session.
  - j: Telegram from Norfolk and Western Railway Co.
  - k: Regulations drawn up by Board of Visitors for general scholarships.
  - l: Article in Encyclopedia Americana about V.P.I., history and statistics etc... May 11, 1904.
  - m: Letter concerning the amendment to the mining bill H.R. 8868 as proposed by the National Association of State Mining Schools and Invitation to their convention of Association of American Agricultural colleges and Experimental Stations.
  - n: Notable letterhead from the Louisiana Purchase Exposition Commission with a pamphlet of editorials from newspapers on the undertaking of a Virginia building at St. Louis.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence. (Box-folder 1:26)
  - a: Letter to Virginia State Board of Crop and Pest Commissioners regarding experimental work and funding, written by J.L. Phillips, State Entomologist.
  - b: Letter to Dr. Campbell from William Thorton Office of the dean on how the University of Virginia deals with delinquent students.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Pillsbury-Washburn Flour Mills Company Ltd.
  - d: Document calculating out deficits of the school.
  - e: Letter to Vawter from the Board of Visitors in response to his resignation.
  - f: "Memorandum of working agreement between the State Board of Control of Virginia and the Bureau of Animal Industry for the Control of Southern Cattle and the eradication of Ticks which transmit Southern Cattle Fever."
  - g: Article titled " Farmers Arrange for Institute." discussion of the program for the Ninth annual Farmers' Institute.
  - h: Comparison of Cost of Work provided for in Bill reorganizing the Department of Agriculture, when work is done be the Department of Agriculture and when it is done by the Agricultural Experiment Station.
  - i: " An agreement between the State board of Agriculture and the board of control of the Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station and the Southern Produce Co., Representing the Truckers of Virginia, for the establishment and management of a station in the trucking section."
  - j: letter from McBryde, reasons for asking for increase of 10,000 dollars in annual appropriations.
  - k: Review of the history and standing of the V.P.I. Veterinary department.
  - l: In depth notes on a visit to V.P.I. including corps, barns and buildings, unknown author.
  - m: Direct appropriation since 1891, Exclusive of 60,000 last granted.
  - n: A bill to apply a portion of proceeds of sale of the public lands to the endowment support and maintenance of schools or departments of mining and metallurgy in the several states and territories in connection with the colleges for the benefit of Agriculture and the Mechanic Arts established in accordance with the provisions of an act of congress approved July 2, 1862.
- Abbot-Allen, 1900-1904. (Box-folder 1:27)
  - a: General correspondence from parents and relatives asking for information.
  - b: Notable letterhead from the State Board of Agriculture.
  - c: Notable letterhead from David M. Lea and Co.
- Ambrose-N.W. Ayer and Son Advertising, 1900-1904. (Box-folder 1:28)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Anderson & Co., 1900.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Central Mfg. Co., 1904.
  - c: Flyer for a book for students of the Drill Regulations of Infantry Drill including interpretations of the drill by Lieut. John T. French, Army & Navy Journal.
  - d: Notable letterhead of Aspinwall Manufacturing Co. Potato Machinery.
  - e: Notable letterhead for the Iowa Homestead, a western farm journal.
  - f: Announcement of participation in inter-state travel for Cornell Universities Sports teams, 1901.
  - g: Manual of the rules of guidance for students, September 1901.
  - h: Notable letterhead for Wingo, Ellett & Crump Shoe Co.
- Baach-Beinkampen, 1900-1904. (Box-folder 1:29)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Baldwin's Deteribes, 1902.
  - b: Pamphlet and price list advertising the Klip Binder by the H.H. Ballard Co.
  - c: Notable letterhead Barnes-Crosby Co.
  - d: Notable letterhead from James S. Barron and Company.
- Beinkampen-Blount, 1900-1904. (Box-folder 1:30)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Quinn-Marshall Co.